Yeah. Brilliant.
All right.
Good.
Well good morning.
From the eastern time zone to everyone.
Not sure where it is, what time it is,
wherever you all are in the world.
But today we are officially starting day
four of ello.
in mind, partly artistic,
but also partly engineering and focus.
So welcome back to welcome.
And welcome back to the Algorithms
and Imaginaries track.
We'll go ahead and get started here.
So our first presenter this morning
well morning for me
the kind of themes I've done in the past
about how we sense, how we make sense
is Tiffany Fung with coding A Poetics
of Love and Politics on the remixing
potentials of Christopher Strategy
and Liliana von Bertram's poem generators.
Tiffany,
if you'd like to go ahead and get started.
What other stories would be
told through these systems?
Okay. Can you guys hear me?
All right. Good. Okay.
I'm also going to time myself
just to be safe.
more than perhaps what you might think of
as a typical elite project,
Okay. Well. Hi, everyone.
but it has got elements that resonate,
and it certainly comes from a place
My name is Tiffany.
And good evening to you all from Hong
Kong.
I'm a student
in the Chinese University of Hong Kong,
and I'm going to be talking about
poem generators today, so.
I come from the Nam
June Paik school of using technology
to despise it properly, and we have enough
celebrations of technology.
The intersection of
love and politics has been the key
concern of contemporary poetics.
And when the poet Jericho Brown writes
that every love poem
is political,
every political poem must fall in love.
The heart of this project
is a consideration of environmental
I take this as a provocation to ask,
what about poem generators?
How is a love poem generator political?
And how can a political poem
generator fall in love?
and thinking about
what are their implications
for seeing and thinking going forward?
So to answer these questions,
I will look at Christopher Strategy's Love
Letter Generator in 1952 and also
a new sermon on the work land from Lilian
Yvonne Bertram's travesty Generator,
who I think is here with us today.
the waste that's generated at every stage
of the lifecycle of digital technologies.
And I will direct my focus to their data
and code rather than the output.
And I'm looking at all
this through the lens of remixing
That's something
I am not particularly happy about.
as a poetic encoding strategy,
as well as a means to maintain
relational kinship
with one's communities of practice.
AI technologies have been critiqued
for their environmental impact,
So, first of all, why code and data
instead of the output?
Both of both of these generators
are programed to produce
came onto the scene,
and it was certainly not looking good.
output on an infinite loop.
So the sheer number of possible
combinations
in their textual output
simply makes close reading efforts futile.
generalized, mythologized sense
in which they're pitched towards us.
And if, as John
Kelly puts it, that a potential for human
reading is required to produce
an event of language,
They're advanced analytical techniques.
then the inexhaustible generative
possibilities of the output
makes it impossible to meaningfully
read them as a complete body of work.
and we don't have to worry
too much about their impacts as a result.
It sort of obstructs meaningful
reading on the human readers part
And that has been fairly robustly
critiqued as a load of greenwashing.
to produce an event of language,
and in that case,
the code that enables this infinite
generative ability
becomes the finite and legible artifact
where meaning unfolds,
map and model about the world
realistically.
Nevertheless,
we are here, and it is very likely,
and specifically
in the case of strategies.
Love letter generator.
The contextual parameters
that could guide meaning
I think, that this technology
in its current form, will persist
making approaches are largely absent.
So if we take this letter output here
as an example,
through which environmental issues
are seen and understood by many people.
when I was reading it, I was asking
questions like who is writing to who?
And what is this passionate
wish of the receiver?
And where is this
wistful sympathy coming from?
Did something happen?
Which makes sense,
because when you're reading a love letter,
you would expect there to be some context
based on the relationship
between two people.
And the sentiments here are specific
enough to provoke these questions,
but they cannot be answered
because the combinations of these phrases
are the result of
aleatoric computational processes.
emulating human modes of thought,
human imperatives, human agency,
So the tension created here
is the reason why
but actually drawing our attention to the
more than human world or non-human world.
wardrobe fun refers to the generators
textual output as something
that is not working toward the pleasures
traditionally found in reading.
and how the impact our daily lives.
It demands us to read the generator
not by what it out
puts, but by its code,
where meaning resides as poetry.
inspired by this call.
I'm equating strategies
generator with poetry here because
I feel like his code works
with formal constraints,
like templates and preset data
to generate ideas and surprising language,
which is very similar
to poetic constraints.
Very, very small compact package
that is small enough, light enough,
So, having established my approach,
how can data and processes in strategies
code be politically subversive?
You can carry it aboard a kite
rather than a drone, as we might
Strategy himself
thinks that the vocabulary vocabulary data
that he took from Roget's saurus lends
a peculiar flavor to the output.
As you can see from the example just now.
And I think this peculiarity lies
in the dissonance of using a standardized
language repository as data to compose
love letters, which is a general
Let's make AI small again.
that usually employs
a really personal and private language.
And that is probably also
why many have thought of his generator
as a queer critique
of normative expressions of love.
a awful lot that I could say
about the technology of this program,
what I'm doing with it, and
I just don't have the time to go into it.
So to
unpack what this queer critique entails,
I look at how the use of a source
Now, essentially,
it consists of a large lifting kite.
as data instead of a dictionary manifests
as a kind of queer subversion.
In this case
it was a big eight foot Delta Conine.
In a source entry, a word is grouped with
other words that share similar meanings.
So the meaning of a word is built with
and around
its relations, both immediate
and distant with other words.
Attached to that is a small computing
package, typically a Raspberry Pi.
A dictionary entry, however, stresses on
an exactness and meaning, and a position
in equivalence when it comes
to the definitions of a word.
I've primarily been working with images
because that's what I understand best.
So comparing how these two sources
organize and attribute
Hopefully very, very soon.
meaning differently, the source suggests
something clear to me
what the Raspberry Pi is doing
is it's taking in that data,
because it defines a word
by measuring its proximity and likeness
feeding it into a small, large vision
model
with other entries,
which can range far and wide,
and setting various tasks
and analysis on it.
it is more capacious in holding
multitudes, variations and affinities
in what a word can signify,
rather than insisting on an absolute
exactness and meaning,
and this evokes a sense of queerness.
So for him to use the source as data
And frankly pulling them to work,
seeing what they can do.
is to sort of
code queerness into its data.
The whole lot is controlled
in a manner typical of a drone actually.
So there's a
there's a kite net, you log into the kite,
And with that
said, strategy then reimagines
the love letter
as a space for preserving queer love
with the generative nature of the code.
commands to be up
linked video, imagery and data to be down,
And essentially, if you don't physically
pause the code execution,
the loop just runs the system
repeatedly and infinitely,
and the act of composing love letters
infinitely and in endless amounts
Then we've gone to all the trouble
of hauling it up.
is itself a testament to the capacious
and boundless energy
So in terms of visual data,
of a love that could essentially outlive
even the lovers themselves.
go, okay, I have this scene before me
at an altitude of 200ft.
So I see this as strategy's way
of animating and preserving queer love
by programing it, to be generative,
to be able to run forever.
And this is how its generative
potential resists a political reality
that threatens to silence queerness
and queer love.
I'm bringing it down here and saying,
okay, classify
this terrain according
to these different land class types.
And with that said,
I've also noticed that the operation
and form of the generators code
welcomes a remixing possibility,
and it only gets worse
the smaller they get.
because you can imagine
substituting the source data set
very difficult to get it to pay attention
to the natural world.
with a completely different input source,
or to change up the template
order slightly, which will then produce
entirely different output results
that reimagine different kinds
of interpersonal relationships
and also different ways
of falling in love.
And even when it does point out a natural
scene, it's like there was a bush.
And I think that this really mixing
potential unsettles
the sexual political order
that assigns the writer
who gets to express
love and desire freely.
So these possibilities, implied
by the choice of data and processes,
become a productive and generative force
to rework the status quo.
are so different from the rich works
of environmentally literature
that we are used to think of J.R.
And in light of the above,
I will now bring the same logic
Carpenter's works, for instance.
on remixing
to my reading of Lillian Yvonne
Bertram's A New Sermon on the War
planned a poem by algorithm.
we had the kind of documenting
The code is not publicly available,
I believe.
and really got this idea
of more than human
I think it used to be
from my digging of it,
but I don't think it is anymore.
But we do know from the creative statement
and the poem output
that it works in a similar logic strategy
generator
of doing anything remotely as clever
as that without a lot of work.
as seen from this possible template
that I wrote here.
But remixes
a coding and poetic strategy doesn't stop
at the level of the systems processes.
By situating their writing
and coding practice
as inherited from a range of poetic
and algorithmic ships.
There are so many things they don't do,
they don't do well.
The politically subversive purposes
of digital remixing in this generator
at to highlight their failures,
to highlight their failings.
ultimately becomes
also an ardent expression of love.
And ultimately, by way of that,
getting us to remind ourselves of a world
So I've put here
the communities of practice
that Bertram shares a relational kinship
with through remixing in this poem
generator, and I am suggesting
that remixing is how Bertram initiates
and maintains this kinship,
because remix theory puts
a lot of emphasis on acknowledging
and honoring one's artistic lineages.
But nevertheless, you might think, okay,
where's the angle going on in all of this?
For one, it's to avoid plagiarism,
but more importantly,
it is to expose a dependency of a work
on a preexisting context
that enables it to generate meaning.
I should say, is once the system
classifies the landscape,
those classes and those short descriptions
associated with each class in terms of
And if remixing is guided by an attention
toward
how one's creative work is always situated
in relation to other histories
and realities, then code, or in this case
Bertram's poetry generator, must exist
as a political artifact
that is shaped by the haunting legacy
of racial violence
against black Americans,
and this relationality also manifests
from a collective effort to fashion
a voice for the unimagined black coders,
which I see as a gesture
of love from Bertram
to their communities of practice.
So the idea is that
the system is actually using what it sees
But of course, this remixing of codes
and data is not just for the sake of it.
as a framing query,
and is overlaying the visual landscape
To understand how it is a gesture of love,
I will now turn to Gwendolyn Brooks
with some of these extracts from these,
The Sermon on the Warp Land,
which not only inspired the title
of the poem generator,
but it's also worked into the data of it.
And I wanted to direct you
to the last stance of the poem here,
where Brooks sort of builds
a voice to call for a sense of unity
among the black community.
I see a poetic and algorithmic
convergence in Brooks's text here,
So it sees a distant hill,
it sees a river, it sees a farmland.
because whether you read it
as poem or code, it functions
as a set of executable instructions.
This is her rallying cry
to her people to build a future
that embraces the multitudes of blackness.
And this future is built with a love
like black are black.
And I think that this is the mantra
that Bertram bears out in a new sermon,
Reading the landscape
as a prompt for reflection,
because they show that they are conscious
of this relationality
by remixing the legacies of their poetic
and algorithmic predecessors,
because no one is doing anything in coding
without someone else.
Teams of others, in fact,
and more importantly,
Bertram is taking up this continuous work
by positioning
themselves as an unimagined coder
in writing and coding.
So coming up to near the end, very good.
Travesty generator computing practices
have historically excluded
people of color, women, and those from
lower socioeconomic backgrounds,
I've had to be very schematic.
and while there have been
increasing efforts at making computation
a more accessible resource
for them, attaining algorithmic literacy
remains a former privilege
that renders these individuals unimagined.
Readers and coders of algorithms,
let alone black experimental code work,
and by being explicit in their positioning
as an unimagined black programmer
It's unlikely to achieve that aim, but
that's part of the esthetic aspirations,
whose code confronts the oppressive
political reality of their people.
this idea of imagining another world
and imagining another world.
Bertram's work is also an intervention
into a literary
and computational space
that has long excluded people of color,
what are the challenges
involved in doing so?
and I think that at its core,
this intervention is motivated by love.
quite important to me in terms of modeling
what another world would look like,
Bertram's intention with programing
the unimagined coder into existence.
what another sort of speculative sensory
landscape may ultimately resemble as well.
And eventually what I hope to do
is because the thing
It advocates
for a new narrative
where there can be more black coders
and poets experimenting with this literary
and computational practice.
I'd love to be able to do performances
with this apparatus.
What Gwendolyn Brooks cause
a lot like black are black
is exemplified by their commitment
to amplifying the voices
and realities of the black community.
We can annotate the data
that it's generating in real time,
And sort of code is something
that has meaning beyond its functionality
as a form of symbolic expression
and interaction.
Then it can be said that love,
specifically a love embodied in honoring
once lineages and inheriting the work,
inheriting the work of community advocacy.
That's what Bertram's code is expressing
and interacting with.
Thank you very much for listening.
And finally, I would like to end
with this quote from Jacob Brown,
who says, when I say I love you,
I mean for you to understand
that I exist in relation to you.
And I really like this quote,
because I think it perfectly encapsulates
the relationality that strategy and
Bertram bear out in their home generators.
And ultimately,
I think that there is no greater
act of love than centering your craft
around your communities and relations,
despite the political circumstances
that threaten to sever these ties.
This is my list of works,
and that is all I have for you today.
Thank you very much.